Let's put together our custom hook. Remember, the entire
커스텀 훅을 만들어 봅시다. 여기서 전체
goal here is to prevent Claude from ever reading the contents
목표는 Claude가 절대 .env 파일의 내용을 읽지 못하게 하는 것입니다.
of the .env file. In the last video, we
지난 영상에서 저희는
discussed many of the different configuration options we'll need to
필요한 다양한 설정 옵션에 대해 논의했습니다.
set, so in this video, we'll be mostly focused on the implementation.
그래서 이번 영상에서는 주로 구현에 초점을 맞출 것입니다.
To get started, inside the . Claude directory, I'm
시작하기 위해 . Claude 디렉토리 안에서
going to open up the settings.local.json file.
settings.local.json 파일을 열 것입니다.
Remember, inside of here, we have a list of pre-tool
기억하세요, 이 안에는 사전 도구 사용
use hooks and post-tool use hooks.
훅과 사후 도구 사용 훅 목록이 있습니다.
As we discussed a moment ago, we want to make a pre-tool
방금 논의했듯이, 저희는 사전 도구 사용
use hook so that we can prevent Claude from ever reading the contents
훅을 만들어서 Claude가 해당 내용을
of that particular file. I already added in
읽지 못하도록 막고 싶습니다. 저는 이미
a little configuration section right here for us, just to
타이핑을 조금이라도 줄이기 위해 이곳에
save us a little bit of typing. All we need to do is
작은 설정 섹션을 추가했습니다. 저희가 해야 할 일은
fill in the matcher and the command. First
매처와 명령을 채우는 것뿐입니다. 먼저
is the matcher. So the matcher is going to be the tools
매처입니다. 매처는 저희가
that we want to watch for. In our case, as
주시할 도구들입니다. 저희 경우,
we discussed, we want to watch for calls to the read
논의했듯이, read와 grep 도구에 대한 호출을
and the grep tools. I'm
주시하고 싶습니다.
going to separate those two tool names with a pipe symbol.
두 도구 이름을 파이프 기호로 구분하겠습니다.
So that's not an L or a capital I. It is
그것은 소문자 l이나 대문자 I가 아닙니다.
a symbol right above the return key on your keyboard. Then,
키보드의 return 키 위에 있는 기호입니다. 그런 다음,
next up, we need to provide a command to run whenever
다음으로, Claude가 해당 두 도구를 호출하려고 할 때 실행할
Claude attempts to call those two tools. We
명령을 제공해야 합니다. 저희는
could put in here any command you want, so it can be a CLI,
원하는 어떤 명령이든 여기에 넣을 수 있습니다. CLI가 될 수도 있고,
it can be a call to a shell script, absolutely anything.
셸 스크립트를 호출하는 것이 될 수도 있고, 정말 무엇이든 가능합니다.
To follow the pattern that I've already established inside the rest
이 파일의 나머지 부분에서 제가 이미 설정한 패턴을 따르기 위해
of this file, I'm going to call a node.js
저는 미리 hooks 디렉토리에 넣어둔
script that I placed ahead of time inside the hooks directory
node.js 스크립트를 호출할 것입니다.
of this project. So inside the hooks directory, I
따라서 hooks 디렉토리 안에서 저는
put together for us a read_hook.js
read_hook.js 파일을
file. This is the file that I want to run whenever
만들었습니다. 이 파일이 Claude가
Claude attempts to call one of those two tools.
이 두 도구 중 하나를 호출하려고 할 때 실행되기를 원하는 파일입니다.
So to call that, I'm going to replace the true right here, which
그것을 호출하기 위해, 저는 지금은 플레이스홀더인 이곳의 true를
is just a placeholder for right now, with node
node ./hooks/
./hooks/
read_hook.js로 바꿀 것입니다.
read_hook.js. I'm
이 파일을 저장하겠습니다. 그러면
going to save this file and that's all we have to do inside
여기서는 이것으로 충분합니다. 다음으로는 Claude가
of here. Next up, we need to actually implement
read 또는 grep 도구를 호출하려고 할 때마다 실행될
the command that's going to run anytime Claude tries to call the
명령을 실제로 구현해야 합니다. 그것은
read or the grep tools. So that's going to be the read_hook.js
read_hook.js 파일이 될 것입니다. 이 파일의 맨 위에는
file. At the top of this file, I've got some code
표준 입력을 읽고 데이터를
that's going to read from standard in and parse that data
JSON으로 파싱하는 코드가 있습니다.
as JSON. So this tool args
따라서 이 tool args 객체는
object right here, that's going to be the big JSON object I showed
이곳 다이어그램에서 보여드렸던 큰 JSON 객체가 될 것입니다.
you in this diagram back over here. So it's going to have properties
따라서 session ID, tool 이름, tool 입력과 같은 속성을
like session ID, the tool name, the tool input,
가지게 됩니다. 그래서 저희가 정말 해야 할 일은
and so on. So all we really need to do is
바로 저 파일 경로를 살펴보고
take a look at that file path right there and decide whether
그것이 .env 파일을 읽으려고 하는지 여부를 결정하는 것입니다.
or not it is trying to read the .env file. If
만약 그렇다면, 저희는
it is, then we want to make sure that we exit from
프로그램이나 명령어에서 종료 코드 2로 종료되도록
our program or our command here with an exit code
해야 합니다. 그리고 가능하다면 Claude에게
of two. And hopefully also log some information
"죄송하지만 해당 파일은 읽을 수 없습니다"라는 로그를 남겨서
out to Claude that says, sorry, but you can't read that file.
정보를 제공하면 좋습니다.
So you'll notice that back over here, I've already got some code that's going to read that
그래서 여기에서 제가 이미 해당 파일 경로를
file path. You'll also notice that there is a
읽는 코드를 가지고 있다는 것을 알 수 있을 것입니다.
fallback of looking at toolInput.path
또한 이곳의 toolInput.path를
right here. I'll tell you why that's added in in just
보는 대체 경로가 있다는 것을 알 수 있을 것입니다.
a moment. So now let's implement the to-do
잠시 후에 왜 추가되었는지 설명해 드리겠습니다.
statement. We'll say if readPath includes '.env',
이제 to-do 문구를 구현해 봅시다. readPath에 '.env'가 포함되어 있다면
that means that Claude must be trying to read the .env
Claude가 .env 파일을 읽으려고 하는 것이라고
file. And if that's the case, then I want to make
말할 것입니다. 만약 그렇다면, 저희는
sure that we block that operation and provide some logging
해당 작업을 차단하고 Claude에게 로그 피드백을 제공해야 합니다.
feedback to Claude. So I'm going to first add in a
그래서 먼저 console.error,
console.error, specifically a console.error,
정확히는 console.error를 추가할 것입니다.
because we want to log to standard error. Remember, that's
왜냐하면 표준 오류에 로그를 남기고 싶기 때문입니다. 기억하세요,
how we provide some feedback to Claude. And I'll say something
그것이 Claude에게 피드백을 제공하는 방법입니다. 그리고 저는
like, "You cannot read the .env
"You cannot read the .env file."과 같이
file." And then I'll do a process.exit(2).
말할 것입니다. 그런 다음 process.exit(2)를 실행하겠습니다.
So now to test this out, I'm going to save the file. I'm
이제 테스트하기 위해 파일을 저장하겠습니다.
going to open up Claude Code. If you already have it
Claude Code를 열 것입니다. 이미
open, make sure you restart Claude Code. You
열려 있다면, Claude Code를 다시 시작해야 합니다.
have to restart it to have any changes to your hooks take effect.
훅의 변경 사항이 적용되려면 다시 시작해야 합니다.
I'm going to ask Claude to read the .env
Claude에게 .env 파일을
file. And it's probably going to attempt
읽으라고 요청할 것입니다. 그리고 아마 시도할 것입니다.
to, but as it attempts to read it, we're going to
하지만 읽으려고 할 때, 저희는
send back an error that says "You cannot read the .env file."
"You cannot read the .env file."이라는 오류를 보낼 것입니다.
And Claude is hopefully going to realize that, sorry, you can't
그리고 Claude는 아마도 죄송하지만 읽을 수 없다는 것을
actually read this. As a matter of fact, it's even able to recognize
깨달을 것입니다. 사실, 읽기 훅에 의해 차단되었다는 사실조차 인식할 수 있습니다.
that it was prevented by a read hook. Now,
이제 저희의 훅은 grep 작업에서도
our hook should also be working on grep operations as
작동해야 합니다. 그래서 Claude에게 grep 도구를
well. So if I ask Claude to try the
사용해 보라고 요청하면
grep tool, This should also
이것도 금지되어야 합니다.
hopefully be forbidden as well. So let's see how it
어떻게 되는지 봅시다. 네, 똑같습니다. 이제 금지되었습니다.
does. And yep, same thing, it is now forbidden.
따라서 이것이 저희가 만든 작동하는 훅입니다. 이제
So that is a working hook that we have put together. Now
이 훅은 그다지 유용하지 않으며, 잠시 후에
this hook is not terribly useful, and I'm going to show you
훨씬 더 유용한 훅을 보여드리겠습니다.